<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on DYREHAUGEN</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on DYREHAUGEN</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ukraine and the future of Nato</title>
      <link>/post/2022/03/10/ukraine-and-the-future-of-nato/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2022/03/10/ukraine-and-the-future-of-nato/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s day 14 of Putins invasion in Ukraine. More than 2 million Ukrainians have fled the bombardments. Ukrainians are fighting heavily back - delaying the Russians.
Ukraine is asking Nato to establish a &amp;lsquo;No-fly Zone&amp;rsquo; - and enforce it! Nato say&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;No&amp;rsquo;. Ukraine is asking for fighter jets. Poland has offered Soviet-era MIGs - if the alliance takes the responsibility of delivry into Ukraine. (Transfer them to Ramstein and let the US send them to Ukraine).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewell Globalization</title>
      <link>/post/2021/05/30/farewell-globalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/05/30/farewell-globalization/</guid>
      <description>To solve the Climate Crisis increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency is not sufficient. Absolute decoupling of economic growth and environmental degradition, including global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?). We will have to stop economic growth itself or even degrow on a global scale.
Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a steady state. That&amp;rsquo;s just mathematics. Many economists have been thinking about &amp;lsquo;steady state economics&amp;rsquo; for a long time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Curse of Development</title>
      <link>/post/2021/05/17/the-curse-of-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/05/17/the-curse-of-development/</guid>
      <description>There exists a well-known Swedish song from my childhood. It begins like this:
Lyckliga gatan, du finns inte mere Du er försvinnen med hela kvarteret ...  In English the meaning would be:
Oh Happy Street of my Childhild you no more exits You are now gone together with the whole quarter ...  The lyrics profondly catches the sorry mood of someone experiencing the arrival of the &amp;lsquo;Development Machine&amp;rsquo; in their neigbourhood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Case of Norway</title>
      <link>/post/2021/02/26/the-case-of-norway/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/02/26/the-case-of-norway/</guid>
      <description>Nordic differences My Swedish friend Torbjörn just sent me a paper clip containing a notice of a Swedish economics professor commenting on the economic situation in Norway. Lars Calmfors in DN 22 feb 2021. The notice is triggered by his involvement in a Norwegian Green Paper Commision on Labour and Income Policy. NOU 2019:7. The Commision shouldpropose new measures to increase labour participation in Norway.
Internationally the Nordic (sometimes only Scandinavian) countries are mostly treated as fairly much of the same under the heading of &amp;lsquo;The Nordic Model&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Time Soon</title>
      <link>/post/2021/01/12/some-time-soon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2021/01/12/some-time-soon/</guid>
      <description>Some Time Soon - things will be the same, but different.
However, we did not notice the emerging change? - or did we?
 David Roberts tweet the day after the Trump-mob storm on Capitol: Feels like we&amp;rsquo;re trapped in a script, a play, that has been performed several times around the world recently. And even though we know exactly how the fall-of-democracy script plays out &amp;ndash; every beat, every chapter &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;re just trapped, helpless, watching it play out</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Capitalism</title>
      <link>/post/2020/02/20/beyond-capitalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/02/20/beyond-capitalism/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;The Climate Crisis is Capitalism&amp;rsquo;s Waterloo&amp;rdquo; (Yanis Varoufakis)
&amp;ldquo;Black Swan&amp;rdquo; is a label for highly upredictable events with extreme impacts. The concept was made popular by Nassim Nicholas Taleb with his 2007 book of the same title. Some will say the Financial Crisis in 2008 was a black swan. As Queen Elizabeth famously asked the community of Britsish Economists: &amp;ldquo;Why did nobody see this coming?&amp;rdquo; - Although some saw it coming, but not among the mainstream scholars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypergranular Macroeconomics</title>
      <link>/post/2019/01/28/hypergranular-macroeconomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/01/28/hypergranular-macroeconomics/</guid>
      <description>The Bruegel blog of September 4, 2018 reports from the annual Jackson Hole gathering of central bankers. This year the focus was on implications for central banks of the rise of superstar firms and changing market structure. Of particular interest I found the contribution of Antoinette Schoar (MIT Sloan) - as refered by Bruegel:
Antoinette Schoar looks at the financial market, argues that the rapid growth of new digital technologies has created a market dynamic, where many institutions outside the central bank system might soon have much more comprehensive, more accurate and also more timely information than the regulators.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krugmans Explanations</title>
      <link>/post/2018/01/25/krugmans-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/01/25/krugmans-explanations/</guid>
      <description>Mainstream economics failure to &amp;lsquo;see the crisis coming&amp;rsquo; in 2008 is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory. However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &amp;lsquo;good enough for government&amp;rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory, but rather in deficient data collection. Macroeconomists &amp;ldquo;overlooked&amp;rdquo; the institutional changes in the financial sector and did not record appropriate data.
The &amp;ldquo;New Keynesians&amp;rdquo; - i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lost Army</title>
      <link>/post/2017/11/16/the-lost-army/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/11/16/the-lost-army/</guid>
      <description>The Thai districts on the Myanmar border have very mixed ethnic groups and a rough history:
The Shan are not the only ethnic group living here. Ban Mae Aeb is a small village comprising five ethnic groups living togetger. Besides the Shan, the village is home to Chinese, Lahu, Akha and Lua.
The &amp;ldquo;Lost Army&amp;rdquo; - the republic of China&amp;rsquo;s 93rd Division - fled into Burma after their defeat to the communist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use it or loose it</title>
      <link>/post/2017/06/20/use-it-or-loose-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/06/20/use-it-or-loose-it/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I got a reminder from Mars! There is a &amp;lsquo;Starmus&amp;rsquo; conference going on these days, in Trondheim, Norway. One astronaut told about returning to Earth after 43 days in Space - the message being that what you don&amp;rsquo;t use (in Space) you have lost when back (on Earth) - i.e. without gravity your sense of balance get lost - you have to retrain basic mobility capabilities upon return.
So also for elderly people - without exercising mind and body capabilities get lost.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The times they are a changing</title>
      <link>/post/2017/05/28/the-times-they-are-a-changing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/05/28/the-times-they-are-a-changing/</guid>
      <description>End of an era? Donald Trump has been on his first international trip as President of the U.S. European leaders for the first time in postwar history finds they can no longer trust the U.S. Government. Neither in defence (Nato), climate change (Paris Accord) or trade (TTIP). We are experiencing the slow collapse of the hegemonic US era. Gone are the days of the Washington Concensus and the Neoliberal economic doctrine.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
